Guide to the Sir Joseph Banks, Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
"Correspondence"
1785-1809
OSBORN FD10
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.08
(1 volume)
Autograph MS. Collection of autograph drafts of letters to various recipients, including a few letter to Banks from various correspondents, concerning scientific matters, the Royal Society, etc.; includes portrait engraving.
Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a partial inventory of the contents of Osborn fd10. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Botany -- Great Britain; Natural history -- Great Britain; Scientific expeditions -- Africa; France -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- France; Correspondence; Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820; Chenevix, Richard, 1774-1830; Cook, James, 1728-1779; Delambre, J. B. J. (Jean Baptiste Joseph), 1749-1822; Greville, Robert Fulke, Hon., 1751-1824; Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew; Royal Society (Great Britain)
- Osborn fd10: Partial List
  - AUCKLAND, WILLIAM EDEN, 1ST BARON, 1744-1814
    - ALS to Sir Joseph Banks (1743-1820), 1807 Feb 3 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Office for Trade [London]
      1 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Request for Banks to peruse an
      enclosure [enclosure missing]
      endorsed by Banks.
      "Banks Letters," p. 12.
      fd.10/12
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to John Julius Angerstein (1735-1823), 1802 Jun 6 (Box 1)
      Soho Square, London
      Concerns agriculture and the Duke of
      Bedford.
      "Banks Letters," p. 20.
      fd. 10/4
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Pierre Hyacinthe Azias (1766-1845), [1809 Jun] (Box 1)
      [Soho Square, London]
      1 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Concerns the Royal Society of London.
      "Banks Letters," p. 26.
      fd.10/26
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL in 3d person to Henry Bone (1755-1834), 1809 Apr 3 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 19 x 11 cm
      Letter of regrets declining an
      invitation.
      "Banks Letters," p.120.
      fd.10/1
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - ALS (draft) to Marguerite Briquet (1782-1825), [1802 Apr] (Box 1)
      Concerns a portrait lent to Banks by
      Briquet.
      "Banks Letters," p. 153.
      fd.10/25
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to [Antoine Alexis Francois Cadet de Vaux (1743-1828)], 1803 Feb (Box 1)
      Concerns a discovery by Cadet de
      Vaux.
      "Banks Letters," p. 191.
      fd.10/6
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Richard Chenevix (1774-1830), 1804 Sep 19 (Box 1)
      Overton
      2 p.; 24 x 19 cm.
      Concerns Chenevix's researches in
      chemistry.
      "Banks Letters," p. 215.
      fd.10/22
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - ALS (draft) to Jean Baptiste Joseph Delambre (1749-1822), 1804 Jan 30 (Box 1)
      4 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      Concerns English members of the Royal
      Society who are held as prisoners in
      France; expresses gratitude for the
      release of a Mr. Osborn and seeks
      release of Mr. Robert Ferguson.
      "Banks Letters," p. 256.
      fd.10/10
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Jean Baptiste Joseph Delambre (1749-1822), 1804 Jan 30 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
      Concerns nautical almanacs to be
      published.
      fd.10/18
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Robert Ferguson (d. 1841), 1804 Jan 30 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
      Concerns Banks's application to the
      National Institute of France for
      Ferguson's release from prison.
      "Banks Letters," p. 325.
      fd.10/19
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to John Foster, later Lord Oriel, (1740-1828), 1803 Apr 25 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      Concerns a proposed statue in memory
      of a duke.
      "Banks Letters," p. 341.
      fd.10/8
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - ALS to Robert Fulke Greville (1751-1824), [1799 Sep 12] (Box 1)
      [Revesby Abbey, Lincolnshire]
      Concerns sheep; also includes 2
      drawings of the hind-quarters of
      sheep.
      "Banks Letters," p. 373.
      fd.10/29
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Rene Just Hauey (1743-1820), [1801] (Box 1)
      [Soho Square]
      Expresses thanks for books sent to
      Banks; Banks also states that he
      has delivered books to the Count de
      [Bournans] and Mr. Greville.
      "Banks Letters," p. 402.
      fd.10/28
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - ALS (draft) to [Jean Frederic Hermann (1743-1820)], 1802 Feb (Box 1)
      Soho Square
      Concerns proposed additions to the
      collections of the British Museum
      relating to animal anatomy.
      "Banks Letters," p. 408.
      fd.10/2
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Sir Everard Home, 1st bart. (1756-1832), 1798 Sep 30 (Box 1)
      Spring Grove
      2 p.; 23 x 18 cm.
      Cites evidence that birds have
      reason.
      "Banks Letters," p. 419.
      fd.10/15
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Charles Jenkinson, 1st earl of Liverpool (1727-1808), 1804 May 20 (Box 1)
      2 p.;23 x 18 cm.
      Discusses a Mr. Pit [?William Pitt
      (1759-1806)] and the appointment of
      a deputy.
      "Banks Letters," p. 467.
      fd.10/20
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to [James Mario Matra (1746-1808)], 1802 Aug 29 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
      Writing on behalf of the African
      Association to the British Consul in
      Tangiers with regards to an
      expedition to explore Africa.
      "Banks Letters".
      fd.10/5
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - Letter (copy) to [Sir William (Johnstone) Pulteney, 5th bart. (1729-1805)], 1802 Jun 25 (Box 1)
      2 p.;32 x 20 cm.
      Banks declines a requests that he
      serve as an arbitrator.
      "Banks Letters," p. 690.
      fd.10/3
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Bartholomew Rudd (1769-1829), [1801] Aug 16 (Box 1)
      1 p.;23 x 18 cm.
      Agrees to plead the cause of the
      sister of Captain James Cook
      (1728-1779) and discusses Capt.
      Cook's widow.
      "Banks Letters," p. 722.
      fd.10/24
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Sir Benjamin Thompson, Count Rumford (1753-1814), [1804 Apr] (Box 1)
      Discusses the affairs of the Royal
      Society as well as his personal
      health.
      "Banks Letters," p. 816.
      fd.10/23
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Sir Thomas Tyrwhitt (1763-1833), 1804 Dec 21 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
      Concerns rolls.
      "Banks Letters," p. 835.
      fd.10/21
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - ALS (draft) to Charles Grant, vicomte de Vaux (b. 1749), 1802 Jun 16 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 21 x 16 cm.
      Concerns essays and writings relating
      to the Royal Society.
      "Banks Letters," p. 366.
      fd.10/9
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Alessandro Volta, count (1745-1827), 1803 Mar 28 (Box 1)
      2 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
      Concerns the Royal Society and
      introduces a Mr. Bickersteth [?
      Henry Bickersteth, Baron Langdale
      (1783-1851)] and thanks for being
      introduced to a Dr. [? Monk].
      "Banks Letters," p. 847.
      fd.10/7
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to the Directors of the West India Dock Company, 1803 Nov 11 (Box 1)
      Concerns Lord Seeforth, Governor of
      Barbados, and bringing plants from
      Cayenne to the Royal Gardens at Kew.
      "Banks Letters," p. 865.
      fd.10/17
  - BANKS, SIR JOSEPH, BART., 1743-1820
    - AL (draft) to Arthur Young (1741-1820), 1803 May 27 (Box 1)
      Concerns the concerns experiments in
      agriculture and agricultural
      "Banks Letters," p. 889.
      fd.10/16
  - CREASSY, JAMES, FL. 1782-1805
    - ALS to Sir Joseph Banks, bart. (1743-1820), 1805 Feb 5 (Box 1)
      Crawley, Sussex
      1 p.; 32 x 20 cm.
      Concerns the National Plan and
      mentions Lord Sheffield.
      "Banks Letters," p. 239.
      fd.10/11
  - PORTLAND, MARGARET CAVENDISH, DUCHESS OF, 1715-1785
    - AL in 3rd person to Sir Joseph Banks (1743-1820), [1785] Jan 17 (Box 1)
      B: House
      Informs Banks that the nymphaea is
      now in flower.
      "Banks Letters," p. 45.
      Women Writers
      fd.10/14